Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2017 March-May; Accession 2017-S-0028; 1.25 linear feet (3 document boxes, 18 oral histories); 2,662.4 Gigabytes (86 digital video and text files)
  - Jennifer Camper interviewed by Hanna Pennington, 2017 March 19; Camper, Jennifer; Pennington, Hanna
    Jennifer Camper (b. 1957) is a queer Lebanese American cartoonist and graphic designer. She grew up in Madison, Wisconsin and graduated from Reed College in Portland, Oregon, where she studied philosophy and art. She moved to New York City in 1986 and has lived in Brooklyn, New York since 1999. She has been publishing her work in gay publications across North America since the early 1980s. Her work examines themes of race, gender, sexuality, class, and politics. Her comic strip Camper ran in Gay Community News from 1989-1994. She is the author of Rude Girls and Dangerous Women (Laugh Lines Press, 1994), and subGURLZ (Cleis Press, 1999), and the editor of the queer comics anthologies Juicy Mother 1: Celebration (Soft Skull Press, 2005) and Juicy Mother 2: How They Met (Manic D Press, 2007). She is a cartoon editor and teacher. She is the founder and organizer of the biennial Queers and Comics conference.
    In this oral history Jennifer Camper describes growing up in a liberal mixed family in Madison, Wisconsin and becoming politically active and discovering underground comics in high school. The interview focuses on her work as a cartoonist, specifically on the queer cartoonist community, publishing cartoons in gay newspapers and magazines, and founding and organizing the Queers and Comics Conference. Camper reflects on the importance and the decline of gay publications and gay bookstores, and the influence of the internet on queer cartooning. She speaks about moving to New York City in 1986, and her experiences with lesbian bars and the AIDS crisis. She describes finding Arab community for the first time in New York, and founding Assal, a group for gay Arab and Iranian women. She describes the experience of being Arab in New York City after 9/11. She reflects on representation, humor, and sexuality in her work, and discusses how she uses humor to fight injustice. Camper's story documents the important work and history of queer cartooning, and emphasizes the rich diversity and multiplicity of gay life in New York City.
    Camper, Jennifer
    - Video interview of Jennifer Camper
    - Transcript of interview of Jennifer Camper (Box 1)
  - Joan Cendella interviewed by Hannah Schneider, 2017 March 24; Schneider, Hannah; Cenedella, Joan
    Joan Cenedella (b. 1936) is a writer and educator living in Northampton, Massachusetts. Joan spent the early years of her life in Wilton, Connecticut, and after her parents' divorce moved to Manhattan, New York. She lived in New York and went to college for her three degrees there at City College and Bank Street College. She went on to be an educator and administrator at the Bank Street School until she moved to Northampton to be with her partner. They now live together in the Lathrop Retirement Community of Northampton, where she enjoys various hobbies and activities that center around learning, writing, editing, and her dog, Lucy.
    In this Oral History, Joan Cenedella discusses her childhood in Wilton, the divorce of her parents, and how her education in her childhood shaped her future, as she later became an educator and administrator herself. Joan identifies as a liberal, progressive, and a democrat, and discusses issues of race, gender, and sexuality. Joan was not involved in many activist projects during her lifetime, and this interview circles around many times to the differences Joan sees between lesbian generations, in activism, and in her community over time. Joan talks about her work as an educator as well as her lifelong love of learning and writing, which has continued throughout her retirement, as well as her involvement in the Northampton community.
    Cenedella, Joan
    - Video interview of Joan Cendella
      Closed until January 1, 2018
    - Transcript of interview of Joan Cendella (Box 1)
  - Portia Cornell interviewed by Allegra Dufresne, 2017 August 1; Cornell, Portia; Dufresne, Allegra
    Portia Cornell (b. 1937) grew up on a small farm in New York with four siblings. She obtained her undergraduate degree from Swarthmore College and graduated from Bank Street College of Education. Cornell taught at Riverside School and the Ethical Culture Fieldston School in New York City before moving to Hartford, Connecticut in the 1970s and later South Hadley, MA in the 1990s. Cornell has published several collections of poetry. She and her wife currently winter in Gainesville, Florida and spends summers in South Hadley, MA.
    In this oral history Portia Cornell describes her childhood in an upper-class family living on a farm just outside of New York City and her later experiences in lesbian feminist groups in New England of the 1970s and onwards. Cornell covers topics such as being a lesbian teacher in schools, the Hartford, Connecticut bar scene, sexual assault, "coming out" as bipolar to her family, moving to Hartford, Connecticut, the Pioneer Valley, and eventually Gainesville, Florida. She spends a little time talking about her experiences as a lesbian and a bipolar woman in all of these communities, including the retirement community she currently resides in with her wife, Lynne Kimmel. She also discusses her experiences being raised Quaker and the lasting effect that has had on her worldviews and activism.
    Cornell, Portia
    - Video interview of Portia Cornell
    - Transcript of interview of Portia Cornell (Box 1)
  - Kim Evans interviewed by Madison Walat, 2017 March 18; Evans, Kim; Walat, Madison
    Kim Evans (b. 1959) grew up in West Boylston and Holden, MA, at the age of nine Kim moved to West Dennis on Cape Cod. She graduated from Springfield College in 1981 and earned her Bachelor of Science Degree and Massachusetts Teacher Certification in Physical Education and Health K-12. Kim has taught Physical Education in a few schools, and went on to teach Health Education at Longmeadow Elementary School (1993-98). She eventually began her position as a Health Educator at Monson High School, where she currently works. Kim has received several awards for her work as an educator and an activist, dedicated to opening the hearts and minds of those around her. Additionally, Kim has coached Varsity Cross Country and Track and Field as well as taken on the position of Athletic Director of Monson Public Schools. Kim founded the only club at Monson High School for LGBTQ students, and has worked with PFLAG and the Anti-Defamation League.
    In this oral history Kim Evans describes growing up in Cape Cod, being a tomboy and loving sports and athletics. She recounts her college years, heterosexual marriage, divorce, and work as an activist. She describes her life as a mother, a health educator, and cancer survivor. Kim details being a lesbian health educator in a rural area, as well as her marriage to her partner of six years. Within this oral history, Kim confronts the challenges of coming out as a lesbian to her husband and her children.
    Evans, Kim
    - Video interview of Kim Evans
    - Transcript of interview of Kim Evans (Box 1)
  - Judy Fjell interviewed by Eliza Cummings, 2017 March 11; Fjell, Judy; Cummings, Eliza
    See staff for more information.
    Judy Fjell (b. 1950) grew up in Big Timber, a small town in rural Montana. Her mother was an elementary school teacher and her father was a rancher. Judy attended St. Olaf College in Northfield, Minnesota from 1967-1971 where she graduated with a degree in Art and Asian Studies. She is a musician, singer songwriter, and activist who has performed around the world for the last four decades. She spent her twenties, thirties, and forties living in Oregon and Northern California where she performed regularly within the women's music circuit. She started her own label in 1980 called Honey Pie Music and later founded two annually held, women's music empowerment camps. Throughout her musical career she has played on diverse stages including: San Francisco peace marches, NOW conferences, Montana Cowboy Poetry Gatherings, GLBT Pride in Boise, New York City coffeehouses, the Michigan Womyns Music Festival, the Northwest Regional Folklife festival in Seattle, and concerts in Japan working against domestic violence. She currently lives in Helena, MT with her partner of seven-years. She continues to teach and play music promoting humanism, environmentalism, social justice, and spirituality through her work.
    In this oral history Judy Fjell describes her childhood growing up in a small, rural town in Montana as well as her experience living on the West Coast performing as a musician on the women's music circuit. The interview focuses on her experiences as a musician and artist as well as her relationships throughout her life. Judy expresses her thoughts on biphobia and lesbophobia, differences between gay men and lesbians, tension within lesbian communities, the erosion of women's and lesbian spaces, and the current political. Judy's reflections contribute to the field of lesbian history by adding to our knowledge of rural lesbian experiences as well as the growth and then decline of women's music and women's culture.
    Fjell, Judy
    - Video interview of Judy Fjell
    - Transcript of interview of Judy Fjell (Box 2)
  - Rosemary (Rosie) Heidkamp interviewed by Evelyn Mandel, 2017 April 9; Heidkamp, Rosemary; Mandel, Evelyn
    This interview may not be placed on the internet. Researchers may use this interview in the archives only. No recording of this interview is available; researchers may consult a transcript only.
    In order to be allowed access to this oral history transcript, researchers must sign an Access Agreement stipulating that the researcher will not publish identifying information about the individuals in the material.
    Rosemary "Rosie" Heidkamp (b. 1958) was born in Evanston, IL and lived in Levittown, NJ, outside of Johannesburg, South Africa, and Melrose, MA throughout her childhood. Her early experience of rural life in South Africa gave Heidkamp a taste for what she would end up loving and searching for for years. After a few semesters at UMass Amherst, Heidkamp joined Ant Rockies, a commune in Leverett, MA, where she lived from 1979 until 1985, when she and a group of friends decided to buy their own piece of land. During the same time, Heidkamp participated in war tax resistance and sit-ins to stop the construction of nuclear plants. In 1986, Heidkamp moved to Wendell and, over the course of several years, built her own house and created a community that lived by its "Back to the Land" values. Since arriving in Wendell, Heidkamp has also become very involved with the Wendell library, and what began as just filling in a few hours a week turned into applying for and receiving a million dollar grant to implement a new library building in 2006. Since taking over the library, Heidkamp has poured herself into making it a vibrant center of Wendell's little community.
    Heidkamp, Rosemary
    - Video interview of Rosemary (Rosie) Heidkamp
    - Transcript of interview of Rosemary (Rosie) Heidkamp (Box 2)
  - Jane McMahon interviewed by Catherine Hartup, 2017 March 13; McMahon, Jane; Hartup, Catherine
    Jane McMahon (b. 1966) has spent her life in Wisconsin; she grew up in the town of Fond du Lac before moving to the state's capitol, Madison, to earn her Bachelor of Science in English and Secondary Education from the University of Wisconsin-Madison. She went on to receive a Masters in Education from Viterbo University in La Crosse, WI, and is currently in the process of earning her Doctorate in Administrative Leadership from Walden University, an online institution. McMahon has taught English in the Baraboo School District since 1989. She has also held the Director of Curriculum and Instruction title as well as being the District Instructional Coach. McMahon was honored as Wisconsin's Middle School Teacher of the year in 2014, earning her a fellowship and a trip to the White House to meet President Barack Obama. While she continues to work in Baraboo, McMahon recently moved to Poynette, where she now lives with her wife and their three dogs.
    In this oral history Jane McMahon describes her childhood as the youngest of five in a lower middle-class Irish Catholic family. She then describes her college years where she had her first girlfriend and was introduced to gay bars, feminist theory, liberal politics, and activism. The interview explores different women throughout McMahon's life that have had significant influence on the way she experiences the world, from being able to openly and confidently identify as a lesbian to expanding her greater political consciousness. As an educator, McMahon discusses her slow but sure professional coming out, how she strived for her classroom to always be a safe space for students, and the importance of representation in literature and media in correlation with more widespread LGBT acceptance. She also complicates the legalization of same-sex marriage, laments the lack of active support from people without direct connections to the LGBT community, and stresses a love for her own circle of close lesbian friends.
    McMahon, Jane
    - Video interview of Jane McMahon
    - Transcript of interview of Jane McMahon (Box 2)
  - Lisbeth Rivera interviewed by Jennifer Calabrese, 2017 April 7; Rivera, Lisbeth Melendez; Calabrese, Jennifer
    Lisbeth Melendez Rivera (b. 1966) grew up in Caguas, Puerto Rico and graduated from Emmanuel College in Boston, with degrees in Biochemistry and Sociology. Melendez-Rivera's employment history includes working as a phlebotomist lab technician at Brigham Women's and Children's Hospital, serving on the Board of the Massachusetts Coalition for Occupational Safety & Health, and her current position as the Director of Latino and Catholic Initiatives for the Religion and Faith Program at the Human Rights Campaign, among her involvement in many other organizations. She envisioned and directed the short documentary, Before God: We Are All Family, which promotes acceptance of LGBT identities in Latinx communities. For her work, Rivera has been recognized with The Legacy Award, presented by the Women of the Latino GLBT History Project in partnership with the DC Mayor's Office on Latino Affairs and the National Latina Institute for Reproductive Health. Today, Rivera resides in Washington, DC with her partner of twenty years.
    In this oral history, Lisbeth Melendez-Rivera describes growing up in an upper-middle class Catholic family in Puerto Rico and her experience coming to the mainland US by herself to attend an all women's Catholic college in Boston in the 1980s, during the height of the AIDS crisis. The interview focuses on her experience as a lesbian of color working at a hospital during the AIDS epidemic and LGBT life and women's/feminist spaces in Boston during this time period. Rivera also details the influence that Leslie Feinberg, author of Stone Butch Blues, had on her, how she came to present as butch, her relationship with her femme wife, LGBT representation in the media today, and comments on the current relationship between Puerto Rico and the mainland US. Finally, Rivera reflects on her life and activism and offers advice for young and new activists today.
    Rivera, Lisbeth Melendez
    - Video interview of Lisbeth Rivera
    - Transcript of interview of Lisbeth Rivera (Box 2)
  - Kathy San Antonio interviewed by Olwyn Moxhay, 2017 April 10; San Antonio, Kathy; Moxhay, Olwyn
    Kathy San Antonio (b. 1957) was born in Methuen, MA, and grew up in an Italian-American working class family in Lawrence, MA. Throughout her childhood, San Antonio attended Catholic schools, including an all-girls high school. She attended University of Massachusetts Amherst from 1974 to 1978. San Antonio lived in the Pioneer Valley from 1977 to 1983, the Bay Area, California, from 1983 to 1993, Boston from 1993 to 1997, and moved back to the Valley in 1997, where she currently lives. She has worked in a factory office, as a nurse's aide, a medical assistant, a surgery scheduler, a medical secretary, and an administrative assistant. Her current job is an events and scheduling systems coordinator at Smith College, which she has been doing since 2000. She identifies as a lesbian femme, and supports progressive/radical liberal politics.
    Kathy San Antonio begins the oral history by describing her childhood in the working-class town of Lawrence, MA, including her relationship with her family and her experience in Catholic school. She then discusses her time at the University of Massachusetts Amherst, living in the Valley after college, and coming out to her family. San Antonio describes living the Bay Area, California, then moving to Boston and Ashfield, MA, and eventually settling down in Holyoke, MA, where she currently lives with her spouse. In the interview, San Antonio discusses her observations about race and class in the lesbian communities in which she has lived. She mentions the loss of lesbian spaces, and the differences between the lesbian community in the past and today. She also talks about her femme identity and the ways that butch–femme was marginalized in an era when androgyny was the norm within the lesbian community. San Antonio's story also includes her experiences practicing Wicca, and her professional life.
    San Antonio, Kathy
    - Video interview of Kathy San Antonio
    - Transcript of interview of Kathy San Antonio (Box 2)
  - Julie C. Woods interviewed by Kassandra Moore, 2017 May 5; Woods, Julie C.; Moore, Kassandra
    Researchers must sign an Access Agreement in order to be allowed access to the interview.
    Julie Woods (b. 1960) grew up in Carson, California. She graduated from Chadwick School in 1977 and Harvard University in 1981. Woods' employment history includes a variety of technical writing positions and more recently she works as the Urban Bliss Shaman providing business solutions to leaders all over the world. She is the founder of the Fans with Cans movement, a hunger prevention network that has fed over 100,000 families in 4 states. She is also a long time musician and public speaker.
    In this oral history Julie Woods describes her experiences being alive as a black, gay, autistic woman. The interview covers a multitude of topics - her childhood in Carson, CA, spent attending a mostly-white private school, and her adulthood on the East Coast, her experiences with her family as a child and in adulthood, as a student at Harvard counseling and experiencing illness, as someone in gay bar/club culture during the AIDS crisis, and as a black lesbian moving through various degrees of intolerance as she moves through the world. Woods' interview offers insight into the complex life of a person whose type of story is not as commonly heard in the mainstream cultural narrative.
    Woods, Julie C.
    - Video interview of Julie C. Woods
    - Transcript of interview of Julie C. Woods (Box 2)
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2018 March-April; 2018-S-0035; .5 linear feet (1 regular document box); 1,638.4 Gigabytes (95 digital video, audio and text files)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  This accession contains materials received in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
  - Klea Blackhurst interviewed by Sara Hollar, 2018 March 14; Blackhurst, Klea; Hollar, Sara; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history Klea Blackhurst describes her childhood in a Mormon family in Salt Lake City, Utah, her involvement with musical theater as child and teenager, and her experience at University of Utah. The interview focuses on her life in New York City from 1985 to the present, including her romantic relationships, coming out publicly and privately, the AIDS crisis, lesbian spaces, her musical theatre career, and her relationship with her family. Blackhurst recounts her experience with shows such Gypsy, Hello, Dolly!, and Oil City Symphony, including touring across the country and abroad, as well as her solo written and performed show, Anything the Traffic Will Allow. Additionally, Blackhurst details her current involvement with the Lesbian and Gay Big Apple Corps Marching Band and her musical theatre history and performance class "Old School."
    Klea Blackhurst (b. 1963) grew up in Salt Lake City, graduated from University of Utah with a BFA in 1985. She then moved to New York City to pursue a musical theatre career. Blackhurst is most well-known for her roles in Oil City Symphony, Gypsy, and Hello, Dolly!, as well as her Ethel Merman tribute show, Anything the Traffic Will Allow: the Songs and Sass of Ethel Merman, which debuted in 2001 and is still being performed. Blackhurst and her partner, fellow actress Andrea, currently live in New York City with their dog Sprout.
    This interview is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
    Blackhurst, Klea
    - Video interview of Klea Blackhurst, 2018 March 14
    - Transcript of interview with Klea Blackhurst, 2018 March 14 (Box 1)
  - Diane Curtis interviewed by Julia Petersen, 2018 March 12; Curtis, Diane; Petersen, Julia; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
    In this oral history, Diane Curtis describes her childhood in a working-class divorced family and how she got into activist work while attending college in New York. She talks about her work with ACT UP, WHAM!, the Pink Panthers, and the atmosphere and communities of gay activists in New York City at the time (80s-90s.) Her professional legal work around private and family law shifted to advising college students when she moved to Western Massachusetts in 1996. She speaks about parenting in the Valley, about loving teaching, and the lessons she has learned from her activist work. This oral history also revolves around analyzing traumatic events, activism, the trouble and joy of organizing, being a parent, being a butch lesbian, being gender-nonconforming, loving music, and the importance of intergenerational conversation.
    Diane Curtis, (b. 1963) grew up in Bloomington, Indiana. She has worked as a bookkeeper in Berkeley, a professor of Legal Studies, and a research assistant for the Homeless AIDS Project. She got a Bachelor's in Comparative Literature from NYU in 1988, and a JD from NYU in 1994. She lived in New York City from 1985 to 1996 and was involved with ACT UP/NY, WHAM!, and the Pink Panthers. Diane moved to Western Massachusetts in 1996. She lives there still, with her wife, Ellen Leuchs, and their children, Jamie and Romy. She currently works at UMass Amherst, as a Senior Lecturer of Political Science.
    Curtis, Diane
    - Video interview of Diane Curtis
    - Transcript of interview of Diane Curtis (Box 1)
  - Carolyn Dull interviewed by Kyra McClary, 2018 March 14; Dull, Carolyn; McClary, Kyra; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)